[MUSIC]
[背景音乐] 翻译: RyukaSuu |审阅: 19waa Coursera Global Translator Community
So the first thing we need to describe is how are we gonna represent the documents
首先我们需要讨论如何表示
that we're looking at.
我们要考虑的文档
Okay, so perhaps the most popular model to represent a document is something called
也许最流行的一种来表示文档的模型是
the bag of words model,
词袋模型
where we simply ignore the order of words that are present in the document.
这个模型忽略了文档中单词的顺序信息
And the reason it's called a bag of words model is we think of taking a bag,
之所以这个模型被成为词袋模型 假设我们拿一个口袋
throwing all the words from that document into the bag, shaking it up, and
把文档里所有的单词扔进这个口袋 摇一摇
the new document we've created with the words all jumbled up
这样把所有单词都打乱了顺序而生成的文档
has exactly the same representation as I'll describe
跟单词有序的原始文档在词袋模型里对应的表示
as the original document where the words were ordered.
是完全一样的
And what we're gonna do, instead of considering the structure,
与其考虑文档的结构
the order of the words,
或是单词的顺序
is we're simply gonna count the number of instances of every word in the document.
我们要做的仅仅是计算 每个单词在文档中出现的次数
So let's look at a specific example of this.
我们来看一个具体的例子
So in this document we're gonna imagine that there's just one sentence, and that
假设这个文档只包含一句话
sentence says that Carlos calls the sport futbol, Emily calls the sport soccer.
这句话说的是Carlos称足球为futbol Emily称足球为soccer
Actually I guess that's really two sentences, but that's the entire document.
我猜这应该算两个句子 它们构成这个文档的全部内容
And what we're gonna do to count the number of instances
为了计算每个单词在文档中出现的次数
of words in this very short document is we're just gonna look at a vector.
我们考虑一个向量
And this vector is defined over the vocabulary
这个向量定义在我们所考虑的语言的
in whatever language we're looking at.
词汇表中
So maybe one word in our vocabulary is the name, Carlos.
也许词汇表中有个单词是名字Carlos
Another place in this vector is the index for the word sport.
向量中的另一个位置是单词sport(运动）
And then, somewhere else we have the word futbol luckily in our English vocabulary
某个位置是单词futbol （足球） 假设很幸运这个单词在我写的这个英语词汇表里
that I'm writing here and then let's say, Emily is this last entry.
Emily在最后一个位置
What words are we missing?
还差哪个单词?
We're missing the word calls, and of course the word the.
还漏掉了单词calls 和单词the
Okay, so how many instances of Carlos?
好了 所以Carlos出现了几次？
Well, there's only one.
只有一次
How many instances of the?
单词the出现了几次呢?
We have two of the.
我们有两个the
Two of calls, two of sports,
两个calls 两个sport
one of futbol and I forgot the word soccer.
一个futbol 我漏写了单词soccer
One word of Emily and let just throw soccer in here,
Emily一次 让我们把单词soccer放在这里
imagining this was the index and this would be our word count factor with.
假设这就是单词索引 这个是单词统计向量
For this document, every other entry would be zero.
对这个文档来说 其他位置都是0
And all these other entries represent all the other words that are out there in
其他的这些位置对应其他所有在词汇表里的单词
the vocabulary, like the word cat, and
比如单词cat
dog, and tree, and every other word you can think of.
单词dog tree 以及任何你能想到的单词
So it's a very, very long and
所以这是一个很长很长的
sparse vector that counts the number of words that we see in this document.
用来表示单词在文档中出现次数的稀疏向量
Okay, so we talked about this representation of our documents in terms
好了 刚刚我们讨论了仅用单词统计来
of just these raw word counts.
表示文档
This bag of words model.
也就是词袋模型
And now we want to talk about how we're gonna measure the similarity between
现在我们要讨论怎样度量不同文档的相似度
different documents because we're gonna use that in order to find
因为我们将用这个度量来找到
documents that are related to one another and so on, like we talked about before.
与某个文档相关的文档等等 像我们之前讨论过的那样
Carlos is reading an article, so what’s another article he might be interested in?
假设Carlos正在阅读一篇文章 其他他可能感兴趣的文章有哪些呢?
Okay, so imagine that this is the count factor that we have for
假设对这篇关于足球的文章 我们有一个对
this article on soccer, with this famous Argentinian player, Messi.
阿根廷著名球星梅西（Messi）的名字的计数
And then there's another article here that I'm showing in blue and
假设有另一篇文章 在这里显示成蓝色
the associated word counts.
和对应的单词统计
And this article is about another famous soccer player, Pele.
这篇文章是关于另一著名球星贝利（Pele）
Is that right?
是这样发音吗?
>> Pele.
Pele
[LAUGH] So when we think about measuring similarity,
[笑声] 所以若我们想要度量相似度
what we can do is simply look at an element-wise product over this vector.
可以简单地计算这两个向量的点乘
So for every element in the vector, we're gonna
也就是说对向量中的每一个元素
multiply the two elements appearing in these two different count vectors.
我们计算两个单词统计向量对应位置的元素乘积
And add up over all the different elements in this vector.
再把所有乘积相加
So here I've done this math where we have 1 times 3,
这里我写出了计算式子 有1乘以3
all the other elements multiplied to 0,
其他位置元素相乘都是0
except at some point that fifth entry in the vector we have 5 times 2.
除了第5个位置是5乘以2
And if we do this multiplication over the whole vector,
如果就这样将所有位置元素相乘
the sum of these terms is 13.
再求和得到13
So that measures the similarity between these two articles on soccer.
这个数量化了这两篇关于足球的文章的相似度
But now let's compare to another article,
但现在再来跟另一篇文章比较
which happens to be something about a conflict in Africa.
这篇文章恰好是关于非洲某个冲突事件
And so I'm providing the examples of word counts that appear in this article.
这里我写出了这篇文章对应的单词统计向量
And what we see, is when we go to measure the similarities between these articles,
我们看到 当我们用之前向量点乘方法
using the method that I described of element-wise product, and
来计算这两篇文章相似度时
then adding, that the similarity here in this case is 0.
得到相似度为0
Okay, so let's talk about an issue that arises when we
接下来我们说说这种
use these raw word counts to measure the similarity between documents.
用单词统计度量文章相似度的方法的问题
So to do this, let's look at these green and blue articles that we had before.
为了说明 让我们看看之前看过的这两篇绿色和蓝色的文章
And so I'm repeating the word count vectors that we had, and
我再重复一下这两个单词统计向量
what we calculated before was the fact that the similarity between these two
和我们之前计算的这两篇关于足球文章的
articles that are both about soccer is 13.
相似度为13
Okay, but
好了
now let's look at what happens if we simply double the length of the documents.
但是现在我们看看 如果将文档复制成两倍长度将会发生什么
So now every word that appeared in that original document appears twice in this
所以原文档的每个单词
twice as long document.
在这个两倍长文档都出现两次
So, the word count vector is simply two times the word count vector we had before.
所以新的单词统计向量变成2乘以原向量
So, when we go to calculate the similarity here,
所以当我们再次计算相似度时
what we see is now the similarity is calculated to be 52.
这两个两倍长文档的相似度是52
So, let's think about this.
现在我们来想一想
What we're saying is that two documents that
我们刚刚说的是 这两篇文章的
are related to each other in the same way as before.
内容上的联系如之前一样
They're both talking about the same two sports, but
它们都讲的是足球运动
one just is replicated twice is a lot more similar.
但若把每篇文章复制成两倍长度 它们就更相似
We would say, yes, Carlos is a lot more interested in this longer document.
我们说 确实 Carlos对这篇两倍长文章更感兴趣
Then what happened when Carlos was reading the shorter documents.
那么当Carlos在读短的文章时会发生什么
So this doesn't make a lot of sense when we're trying to do document retrieval.
这在我们做文章检索时并不太说得通
And it biases very strongly towards long documents.
这种方法更倾向于长的文章
So let's think about how we can cope with this.
现在让我们想想如何解决这个问题
So one solution
一种直接了当的办法是
is very straight forward where we're simply gonna normalize this vector.
归一化这个向量
So we take this word count vector and
所以我们用这个单词统计向量
we're gonna compute the norm of the vector.
计算向量的范数
And so if you guys remember computing the norm of a vector,
如果你还记得如何计算向量的范数
we simply add the square of every entry in the vector, and then take the square root.
只需要计算向量中元素的平方的总和 然后取其平方根
So, in this case,
举个例子举个例子
we have the square root of 1 squared plus 5 squared plus 3 squared plus 1 squared.
这里我们有1的平方加上5的平方加上3的平方 加上1的平方的平方根
And that happens to be the number and so,
最后计算结果是6
the resulting normalize word count vector is shown on the bottom of the slide here.
得到的归一化后的向量显示在屏幕下方
And what this does is, it allows us to place all of our articles that we're
这种处理 使得我们可以将所有的
considering, regardless of their length, on equal footing.
不同长度的文章 置于平等地位
And then use this normalized vector when we go to do retrieval.
接着 在检索中使用归一化后的向量
[MUSIC]
[背景音乐] 翻译: RyukaSuu |审阅: 19waa Coursera Global Translator Community